<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: chef | MatthewCodes]]></title>
  <link href="http://matthewcodes.github.io/blog/categories/chef/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://matthewcodes.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-14T23:48:09+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://matthewcodes.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matthew Wilson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vagrant and Hyper-V Issues]]></title>
    <link href="http://matthewcodes.github.io/blog/2015/11/04/vagrant-and-hyper-v-issues/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-04T19:44:16+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://matthewcodes.github.io/blog/2015/11/04/vagrant-and-hyper-v-issues</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some annoyances in Vagrant 1.7.4</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>We have been using Vagrant, Chef and Hyper-V for a work project for a few months now, and recently have been running into a few annoying bugs.</p>

<hr />

<p>The first issue caught us out after we upgraded to 1.7.4 from 1.7.2. The error we were getting looked something like this:</p>

<pre><code>The following WinRM command responded with a non-zero exit status.
Vagrant assumes that this means the command failed!

cmdkey /add:xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx /user:DOMAIN\user /pass:Password

Stdout from the command:

Stderr from the command:

Exception calling "RegisterTaskDefinition" with "7" argument(s): "The username or password is incorrect. (Exception from HRESULT: 0x8007052E)"
At C:\tmp\vagrant-elevated-shell.ps1:58 char:1
+ $folder.RegisterTaskDefinition($task_name, $task, 6, $username, $password,1, $n ...
</code></pre>

<p>I could not work this one out and reverted to 1.7.2, after a few months I thought I had gotten a lead on the issue when I noticed that there were a few winRM commands executed on our base box. After reverting them and trying a few different combinations I was still getting the same error.</p>

<p>My next thought was maybe the username needs to be fully qualified with the domain name, I tried adding this into the config in the vagrant file but this caused other errors much earlier in the vagrant up process.</p>

<p>So I jumped onto the VM and edited the PowerShell script mentioned in the error output (<code>C:\tmp\vagrant-elevated-shell.ps1</code>) and prepended the username variable with the domain name, this was swiftly removed after doing a vagrant up as this file is copied to the guest from the host. I edited the host copy and got the same error. As a last resort I added some logging to the script and ran a vagrant up again. This time I noticed that the password was incorrect!</p>

<p>Our password contains dollar ($) symbols and these were being stripped out in the script! I&rsquo;ve been caught by this issue before, PowerShell needs the dollar sign to be escaped by a back-tick (`).</p>

<p>I sauntered over to a colleagues desk to brag at this major victory for mankind and he was like oh yea I&rsquo;ve seen a <a href="https://github.com/mitchellh/vagrant/commit/1dd081d8665134bcb9636d2b49efce0fded4a08c">commit message</a> with a fix for that!</p>

<p>We noticed though that our local version was different than the one in the commit message, the change had been lost by <a href="https://github.com/mitchellh/vagrant/commit/1152b4e1df97fb5f468491954932d4f0c09875b1">this newer commit</a></p>

<p>I forked the vagrant repo, made the fix and submitted a pull request, which you can view <a href="https://github.com/mitchellh/vagrant/pull/6452">here</a> someone else had a similar issue and raised a <a href="https://github.com/mitchellh/vagrant/issues/6421">defect</a> have a look at my comment for the steps on patching your environment.</p>

<p>Hopefully my PR will be available in the next release of Vagrant.</p>

<hr />

<p>Another issue that we were having was our vagrant provision was taking more than 2 hours to complete and was timing out for no reason. I stumbled upon this <a href="https://github.com/mitchellh/vagrant/issues/5506">issue on GitHub</a> which references the same PowerShell modified in our first issue. The file (elevated_shell.ps1.erb) has the following line:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;ExecutionTimeLimit&gt;PT2H&lt;/ExecutionTimeLimit&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Changing this to:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;ExecutionTimeLimit&gt;PT4H&lt;/ExecutionTimeLimit&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Fixed our issue, I&rsquo;m hoping this is also a temporary patch as there is already a <a href="https://github.com/mitchellh/vagrant/pull/6213">PR</a> which makes this value configurable.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
